Yinan (Tom) Xuan

yxuan@ucsd.edu https://www.yinanxuan.com My research interests lie at the intersection of ubiquitous computing and personal tracking. I am interested in enabling what I refer to as **unconscious interaction**, where users' natural unconscious behaviors can be tracked and analyzed to facilitate personalized the usage of computational system. I am hoping to achieve this goal by leveraging both machine learning and my hardware and software prototyping skills.

EDUCATION

University of California, San Diego

La Jolla, CA

Ph.D. in Electrical & Computer Engineering

July 2020 - Present

Expected Graduation: June 2024

M.S. in Biological Science

Sept. 2017 - June 2020

Thesis Topic: Drosophila Gut Imaging Data Collection and Analysis

B.S. in Physiology & Neuroscience

Sept. 2013 - June 2017

Minor: Cognitive Science Honors: MAGNA CUM LAUDE (GPA 3.89/4.00)

EXPERIENCE

Graduate Student Researcher

Oct. 2019 - Present

Advisor: Edward Wang

University of California, San Diego La Jolla, CA

Electrical and Computer Engineering Department, Jacobs School of Engineering

Ubiquitous Data & Computing Lab

• Designed and implemented SpecTracle, a vision-based wearable facial tracking system, which consists of fisheye lens cameras controlled by Raspberry Pi and an image based neural network model. (Under review for CHI 2021)

• Implemented a prototype of a Unity based exercising game on Vuzix AR glasses w/ IMU signals

Graduate Student Researcher

April 2018 – June 2020

University of California, San Diego

La Jolla, CA

Section of Neurobiology, Division of Biological Science

Wang Lab

Advisor: Jing Wang

- \bullet Designed and implemented an olfaction VR device as a novel instrument to observe odor guided behaviors in Drosophila
- Designed, implemented and deployed an image processing software to facilitate bio-imaging data analysis pipeline to profile *Drosophila* intestinal cells' response to different nutrients
- Designed, implemented and deployed an automated solenoid valve control system for perfusion experiments that can independently control up to 22 valves
- Collaborated in building and testing a customized three-photon fluorescent imaging microscope
- Built a feedback controlled temperature based anesthetic platform to facilitate surgery process on *Drosophila*

Undergraduate Student Researcher

Jan 2014 – June 2017

 $University\ of\ California,\ San\ Diego$

La Jolla, CA

Division of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery, Department of Surgery Ongkeko Lab

Advisor: Weg Ongkeko

• Studied the role of long non-coding RNAs in head and neck squamous cell cancer

• Designed and conducted in vitro experiments for various projects

Research Internship

June 2016 - Aug. 2016

 $Ask Gene\ Pharmaceutical\ Inc.$

Camarillo, CA

• Collaborated in cell line development selecting clone cells with the highest titer

• Purified recombinant antibodies using Protein-A Affinity Chromatography

SOFTWARE TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Python, Matlab JavaScript, HTML/CSS, C, Java, C++, SQL (MySQL)

Supervised Machine Learning: Neural Networks, SVM

Unsupervised Machine Learning: hierarchical clustering, k-means clustering, DBSCAN, Gaussian Mixture Model Data Analysis: dimension reduction (PCA, t-SNE, UMAP), signal processing, computer vision / image processing

Mobile Development: iOS (Swift), Android (JAVA)

Frameworks: Bootstrap, React, Node.js

Developer Tools: PyCharm, Unity, Git, Google Cloud Platform

Libraries: OpenCV, pandas, NumPy, PyTorch, SciPy, scikit-learn, Matplotlib, seaborn

HARDWARE TECHNICAL SKILLS

• PCB design

• Prototype w/ microcontroller

• Prototype w/ Raspberry Pi

• Free-space Optics

• Compressed gas cylinder handling

BIO-RELATED TECHNICAL SKILLS

• Mice/Drosophila handling • Cell culture • RNA extraction • qRT-PCR • Transfection

PUBLICATIONS

- Vicky Yu, Mehran Rahimy, Avinaash Korrapati, Yinan Xuan, Angela E. Zou, Aswini R. Krishnan, Tzuhan Tsui, Joseph A. Aguilera, Sunil Advani, Laura E. Crotty Alexander, Kevin T. Brumund, Jessica Wang-Rodriguez, and Weg M. Ongkeko. Electronic cigarettes induce DNA strand breaks and cell death independently of nicotine in cell lines. Oral Oncology, 52:58-65, January 2016.
- Angela E. Zou, Jonjei Ku, Thomas K. Honda, Vicky Yu, Selena Z. Kuo, Hao Zheng, Yinan Xuan, Maarouf A. Saad, Andrew Hinton, Kevin T. Brumund, Jonathan H. Lin, Jessica Wang-Rodriguez, and Weg M. Ongkeko. Transcriptome sequencing uncovers novel long noncoding and small nucleolar RNAs dysregulated in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma. RNA, 21(6):1122–1134, April 2015.
- 3. Angela E. Zou, Hao Zheng, Maarouf A. Saad, Mehran Rahimy, Jonjei Ku, Selena Z. Kuo, Thomas K. Honda, Jessica Wang-Rodriguez, Yinan Xuan, Avinaash Korrapati, Vicky Yu, Pranav Singh, Jennifer R. Grandis, Charles C. King, Scott M. Lippman, Xiao Qi Wang, Andrew Hinton, and Weg M. Ongkeko. The non-coding landscape of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma. *Oncotarget*, 7(32):51211–51222, June 2016.

Membership & Honors

- Member of Phi Beta Kappa Honor Society
- Member of Muir College's Senior Honors Caledonian Society